第三部分：联盟飞船分离，再入和着陆
→ 通往ISS的旅途
原作者名：European Space Agency, ESA
视频来源：youtu.be/-l7MM9yoxII
原视频发布日期：20131111
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
正片在00:37处，可自行空降
地球之上400km
自1998年11月以来的每天
Every day, since November 1998,
国际空间站都在以7778m/s的速度绕地飞行
the International Space Station has been orbiting the Earth at a speed of 28000 kilometres per hour.
抵达国际空间站数月后
Having spent several months on-board the International Space Station,
三名宇航员需要返回地球
the time has come for three of its crew members to travel back to Earth.
联盟号飞船的返程需要三个半小时
The return journey aboard a Soyuz capsule takes three and a half hours.
出发前太空中和地面都有很多准备工作要做
Before it can start, there is a lot of preparation to do both in space and on the ground.
通常联盟号会在哈萨克斯坦着陆
The normal landing site for the Soyuz is Kazakhstan.
由专家组成的地面组会进行细致的操作准备
A group of ground based experts prepare meticulously for this operation.
他们会计算空间站当前的绕地轨道
They take into account the current orbit of the station
然后选择最适合的着陆地点
and then select the most appropriate landing site on the ground.
着陆点由搜救人员检查
The landing site is checked by the search and rescue team,
并确保着陆区域是平坦和空旷的 任何障碍物都有可能给着陆造成困难
to make sure that the terrain is flat and free from any obstructions that could complicate the landing.
搜救人员要能够应对极端气候条件下的突发事件
The search and rescue team is able to operate even in extreme weather conditions.
完成所有的信息分析后
When all the information has been analysed,
理想的轨道就被计算出来了
the optimal return trajectory is calculated.
One week before the Soyuz undocks from the station,
在联盟号离开空间站前一周
任务控制中心，俄罗斯，莫斯科
the instructors and controllers located in the Mission Control Centre near Moscow
位于莫斯科附近的任务控制中心的指挥控制人员
远程指导飞船上的宇航员使用搭载的模拟器进行训练
conduct a remote training session with the crew and the on-board simulator.
这时 宇航员们会熟记
During this session,
再入时需要进行的最重要的操作
the crew are reminded about the most important actions they will have to perform during the re-entry.
他们需要仔细复习每个关键步骤的程序
They carefully run through the procedures for each critical step,
包括可能要进行紧急下降的情况
including the scenarios that could lead to an emergency descent.
他们也会得知返程中的最新细节
They are also briefed on the latest details of their trip back,
例如着陆条件 以及精确的航天器系统的启动时间表
such as landing conditions, and the precise timelines for the activation of vehicle systems.
登船的宇航员要测试联盟号的运行
The on-board crew runs a test of the Soyuz vehicle
并打包需要和他们一起带回地球的物品
and begins packing items that will travel with them back to the ground.
然后联盟号启动 宇航员准备脱离空间站
The Soyuz is then activated and the crew starts preparing it for undocking.
在地面控制人员发出指令后
When instructed by the ground controllers,
将要返回的宇航员和留在站上的同事道别
the crew say their goodbyes to their colleagues staying behind,
并且关闭舱门 使联盟号轨道舱与空间站分离
and close the hatch that separates the Soyuz orbital module from the Station.
舱口会被仔细检查
The hatch is carefully checked,
以确保密封 不会造成意外的舱内失压
to make sure there are no leaks that could cause an unexpected cabin depressurization.
宇航员穿上太空服并进入返回舱
The crew members put on their spacesuits and enter the descent module
返回地球的路上会有着终极过山车 般的体验
that they will occupy for the ultimate rollercoaster ride back to Earth.
Former astronaut Frank De Winne is now head of the European Astronaut Centre in Cologne.
前宇航员Frank De Winne现在领导着位于科隆的欧洲宇航员中心
欧洲宇航员中心，德国，科隆
He remembers clearly the emotions he felt as he was about to leave the International Space Station.
他还清楚地记得当初要离开国际空间站时的激动心情
Wow! Today I'm really going home.
哇 我今天终于要回家了
弗兰克·德·温纳
欧空局宇航员
Because of course, the days before, you are preparing for the descent.
当然是因为在这前几天 为准备返航
You are reviewing all the procedures.
你演练了所有的程序
You are going through all the radiograms.
你演练了所有的无线指令
But it is only at the moment that you are in your spacesuit
但是只有当你穿上宇航服
并关闭舱门时 你才知道 四小时之后 你将返回地球
and that the hatches are closing that you know that four hours later you will be back on Earth.
乘员和飞船都已做好了分离准备
Both crew and vehicle are now ready for the undocking sequence.
俄罗斯舱段有不同的连接点来对接联盟飞船
The Russian segments of the station have several docking ports for hosting Soyuz vehicles.
在这个例子中 飞船与通常所说的(处在空间站后方的)服务舱分离
In this example, the vehicle is going to undock from the so called Service Module.
In this case, the undocked Soyuz reaches an orbit below the station.
这种情况下 已分离的联盟号飞船会到达空间站下方的运行轨道
与服务舱(星辰号)分离
The orbital velocity of the Soyuz also increases.
与此同时 联盟号的轨道速度也会加快
但有时 联盟号的对接口处在空间站的下方
Sometimes, however, the Soyuz is docked to a port underneath the Station.
在这种情形下 空间站要在分离前约40分钟时改变方向
In these situations, approximately 40 minutes before the undocking, the Station changes its orientation.
The Soyuz then undocks and joins a higher orbit and its velocity decreases.
之后联盟号分离 进入较高的轨道 同时速度减少
与晨曦号实验舱分离
In both cases, after one revolution of the earth, the orbits intersect.
在这两种情况下 完成绕地一周后 两轨道相交
但由于它们目前处于不同的速度
But because of their now different velocities
空间站和联盟号到达交汇点的时间不同
the Station and the Soyuz arrive at the intersection point at different times.
这避免了两个航天器之间任何可能的碰撞
This prevents any possibility of a collision between the two vehicles.
飞行指挥准备完毕的时候 会给乘员发出GO 指令来开始分离
When the Flight Director is ready, a "GO" is given to the crew to initiate the undocking.
联盟号指令长发出松开联盟号锁扣的指令
The crew commander issues the command to open the Soyuz hooks.
联盟号和空间站只通过这个机械结构来固定在一起
These are the only mechanical devices holding the vehicles together.
大约3-4分钟后 锁扣完全打开
After approximately 3-4 minutes, the hooks are fully opened.
而联盟号不再牢牢地固定在空间站上
and the Soyuz is no longer firmly attached to the Station.
一组在对接时压缩的推杆
A set of pushers that were kept mechanically compressed while docked,
轻轻地把联盟号推出相对空间站0.12到0.15m/s的相对速度
gently ease the Soyuz away from the station at a relative speed of 12 to 15 cm/s.
于美国中部时区21:50确认分离
Undocking confirmed in 9:50 pm central time.
由于离空间站太近 联盟号上的推进系统处于关闭状态
Being so close to the Station, the Soyuz propulsion system is inhibited
以免推进时残留的化学尘埃污染到空间站
in order to avoid contamination of the Station with residual chemical dust produced by the Soyuz thrusters.
宇航员通过舱外的电视摄像机所传递的影像
The crew gets visual confirmation of the separation through the image provided by the external TV camera,
和显示屏上的指示 来确认与空间站的分离
and also from indications displayed on their monitors.
欧空局宇航员Paolo Nespoli在第27远征队任务结束时搭乘联盟号飞船返回了地球
ESA astronaut Paolo Nespoli, returned to earth aboard a Soyuz spacecraft at the end of Expedition 27.
I didn't actually feel the detach, when we detached from the Station.
我完全没有意识到与空间站的分离
保罗·内斯波利
欧空局宇航员
Physically I did not feel it.
身体上毫无感觉
The physical departure from the Station is done because of the push of some springs that are inside.
和空间站物理上的分离时通过内部的弹簧推动造成的
你不想去打开发动机 因为这样会喷出污染物
You don't want to start your engines close to the Station, because you are going to plume everything.
所以你只是漂移开来
So you are just kind of drifting away
而我们所做的只是检查仪器和外部摄像头
and what we were doing was just looking at the instruments, looking at the camera outside
同时确保联盟号在下降通道的范围内
and checking that the Soyuz would be inside the departure corridor.
这就是我们所做的
This is what we were doing.
我没有任何其他感受
I did not really feel anything.
觉得这只是我们返回地球的长途旅程的一个开始
The only thing is that we felt we started this long journey back to Earth.
3分钟后 当飞船移动了大约20米 乘员监视着15秒的点火
Three minutes later, when the spacecraft has moved about 20 metres, the crew monitors the 15 second burn
这将把分离速度提高至0.56m/s
that increases the separation speed up to 2 km/h.
这样联盟号就处在离空间站相对安全的位置上了
This leads the Soyuz to a safe position relative to the Space Station.
完成分离后
After the undocking,
地面控制人员把舱内计算机所需的数据上传 以使下降(再入)过程自动完成
the ground controllers upload the data needed by the on-board computer to autonomously perform the descent.
宇航员始终与地面保持通讯联系
The crew is in constant communication with the ground.
他们要先核对数据的正确性 再交给计算机使用
They verify the validity of the data, before allowing the computer to use it.
在这一阶段 乘员需要特别注意为下一个关键操作做准备 也就是离轨点火
At this stage, the crew must pay special attention to prepare for the next critical operation: the Deorbit Burn.
正如我们所看到的那样 尽管联盟号现在已远离空间站
As can be seen, although the Soyuz is now far away from the Station,
它仍然处于和国际空间站差不多的高度环绕地球飞行
it is still orbiting the Earth at an altitude close to that of the ISS.
离轨点火的目的是迫使联盟号降低运行的速度
The purpose of the Deorbit Burn is to force the Soyuz to decrease its speed.
结果会改变航天器的轨道 使其再入大气层
As a result, the trajectory of the vehicle changes and it re-enters the atmosphere.
大气层就像天然的刹车一样 完成联盟号减速的绝大多数工作
The atmosphere acts as a natural brake and does most of the work in slowing the Soyuz down
直到降落伞打开并确保返回舱的软着陆
until a set of parachutes opens and ensures a relatively soft landing.
这种刹车是通过使用位于飞船尾部的主发动机
This braking is achieved by using the main engine located in the rear side of the spacecraft
产生与运动方向相反的推力来实现的
to push against the direction of travel.
这需要推力的方向和持续时间必须被精确地计算并完成
The required orientation and duration of the braking impulse must be precisely calculated and achieved
因为它们将直接影响再入路径的角度
because it directly influences the steepness of the re-entry path.
如果点火不足 那么我们的速度就太多了
If we don't burn enough, then we have still too much speed
仍将会处在大气层中非常高的位置
and we will still be too high in the atmosphere
实际上会溜出大气层 进入太空中
and we can actually skip off the atmosphere and then go further into space.
当然这样的话再入就失败了
And that of couse would not be a successful re-entry.
另外 如果点火过多 我们进入的角度太陡
On the other hand, if we burn too much and we come in too steep
那么在低层大气我们就会有太多的速度(来不及减掉)
then we will have too much speed when we are in the lower parts of the atmosphere.
而使舱外温度达到摄氏2000度 这样的温度就会有烧毁的风险
The heat that is normally around 2000 degree Celsius will be much higher and we have the risk of burning up.
因此 正确的离轨点火是非常关键的 差不多要120m/s的速度变量
So also therefore is very critical that we do the correct deorbit burn and that we really fix this around 120 m/s.
正确的离轨点火需要主发动机开机4分45秒
To achieve the correct burn, the main engine fires for exactly four minutes and forty five seconds.
此时的联盟号将进入与较密大气层相交的轨道
The Soyuz now follows a trajectory that will lead it to intercept the dense layers of the atmosphere,
这样就能在55分钟后安全地再入并着陆
leading to a safe re-entry and landing, about 55 minutes later.
这期间 飞船沿着轨道飞行约30分钟 然后在140km的高度
As the vehicle travels along its trajectory, about 30 minutes before landing and at an altitude of roughly 140 km,
它分离成三部分 轨道舱 返回舱和设备舱
it separates into three parts: the orbital module, the descent module and the instrument compartment.
轨道舱
仪器舱
返回舱
各舱之间的相互碰撞是不会发生的
There is no chance of the individual modules colliding with each other.
这被称为无碰撞分离
This is called impact-less separation.
只有装有乘员的返回舱能安全返回地球
Only the descent module hosting the crew will make it back safely to Earth.
另外两个舱则会解体并在大气层中烧毁
The other two will disintegrate and burn up in the atmosphere.
船舱的分离在几秒钟内完成
The separation of the spacecraft into three parts is happening through several seconds,
因为这些部件是一个接一个分离的
because there are several parts that get detached one after the other.
所有这些过程都是由爆炸螺栓或者爆炸工具完成的
All of these actions are done with explosive bolts or with explosive implements.
舱内的感觉就像被有人从舱外上下各处用大锤锤击一样
Seen from the inside of the spacecraft, it felt like there was somebody outside the spacecraft with a sledgehammer
上下各处都在锤击
that was hammering here and there, up and down
那么每几毫秒飞船都在震动并邦邦直响
and so every few milliseconds the spacecraft was shaking with this BANG! BANG! BANG! BANG!
实际上这还挺有趣的
It felt really interesting actually!
再入期间 返回舱会经历极高的温度
The descent module experiences extreme high temperatures during re-entry,
那么 为了保护它和它内部的乘员
so to protect it, and the crew inside,
它装有特殊的保护涂层 而它底部还有一个隔热盾
it is fitted with a special protective coating and has a heat shield on its base.
随着大气层越来越密 返回舱变换它的姿态
As the atmosphere becomes more dense, the descent module positions itself
也就是隔热盾会指向前方
so that its heat shield points forward.
返回舱就要进入大气层了
The capsule is about to enter the Earth atmosphere.
这是它回家旅程中最紧张的环节
This will be the most stressful part of its journey home.
在我们再入大气层的时候
By the time we were supposed to re-enter the atmosphere,
实际上我通过窗户看向外面
I actually looked out from our window
我看到我们有点翻滚 我有点沉思
and I actually looked we were tumbling and I was a little bit puzzled
因为我在想我们需要用特殊的角度再入
because I thought we needed to re-enter with a special angle,
所以我开始查看程序
so I started looking at procedures,
我们做了几个操作后继续向外看 我看到我们已进入到等离子层
we did a few things and when I looked out again I saw that we were already inside this plasma,
外面很红而窗口变得很暗
it was getting really red and actually the window was getting pretty dark.
这是因为
What was happening was
等离子流正在燃烧窗户外层的保护层
that the plasma stream was actually burning the outside layer of the window which has a protective cover.
所以这也挺有趣的
So it was kind of interesting.
那时我并没有什么特别的感觉
At that point I really did not feel that much.
我是指 重力开始出现抓着你
I mean the gravity starts grabbing you.
但一开始是很轻微的 你可以用它来感受 或者坐进座椅并系上安全带
But it is very gentle at the beginning and you actually use it to feel or go into the seats and buckle up,
收紧带子 这样你就真正地躺进座椅了
pull your straps so that you really lay into the seat.
真是奇妙的感觉
It was an interesting feeling.
返回舱沿着一种路径下降 这种路径的形状类似冲浪者冲着巨浪
The descent module follows a path that is similar in shape to that made by a surfer riding a big wave.
就像冲浪一样 联盟号可以做出微调以保持下落的轨道
Like a surfer, the Soyuz is able to make small adjustments to keep itself on track.
那么 自由落体的返回舱是如何控制下落的轨道的呢
So, how is the trajectory of a free falling capsule controlled?
尽管联盟号返回舱没有机翼
Even though it does not have wings,
但是联盟号还是可以改变飞行的姿态
the Soyuz capsule is able to change the way it flies through the air.
联盟号是如此设计的
The design of the Soyuz enables it to do this.
返回舱向某一方向转动来增加升力
The capsules lift increases when it rotates in one direction
或者向另一方向转动来减少升力
and decreases if it rotates in the opposite direction.
通过这种方式 返回舱可以保持在预期的弹道上
In this way, the capsule is able to keep to its planned trajectory.
副作用是 这种转动可以使返回舱侧移
As a side effect, this rotation also induces a sideways displacement of the module.
这个效果是非常有用的 因为借助它可以更灵活地选择着陆地点
This effect is very useful because it gives more flexibility for the selection of the landing site.
与此同时 在选择最佳轨迹时 也已经考虑到了这种侧向机动
This sideways manoeuver has already been taken into account when selecting the optimum trajectory.
在大气层中再入的过程中
During the descent in the atmosphere,
乘员会感到减速度的效应
the crew feels the effect of the deceleration
此时他们的重量会数倍于他们处在地面时的重量
when their weight exceeds several times their own weight on the ground.
在返回舱到达差不多35km的高度时 过载会达到最大 也就是4G
The maximum G-load, 4G is experienced when the capsule reaches an altitude of roughly 35 km
此时是再入大气层后6到7分钟时
while it has already been travelling for 6 to 7 minutes in the atmosphere.
重力是很强的力
Gravity is a very, very strong force.
在地球上的时候我们没能理解这样的力
We do not understand here on Earth.
是如何在我们人体和环境中作用的
How gravity has such a hold on our body and what is around us.
可是如果你从太空中返回就会感受到它的作用
You do feel it when you come back from space
因为你已经在较长的一段时间内适应了失重环境
because now you have been in a non-gravity environment for a long time
然而现在你却感受到了重力在抓着你
and then you see all these forces grabbing you.
你看手中的资料 你感觉你的手很重
You look at stuff and you feel your hands are heavy.
你觉得的戴的手表有一吨重 你的书 你周围的物体
You feel your watch weights a ton, your books, the materials around you.
你的头非常重
Your head is extremely heavy.
这的确是一种非常强烈的感受
And it is really a very strong feeling.
如果自动控制系统意外失灵
In the unlikely event that the automatic control system fails,
乘员可以采用备用的手动控制
the crew is able to use a manual hand controller as a backup.
他们对这种情况进行了充分的准备和严格的训练
They train extensively to prepare for this possibility.
另一种选择是弹道式下降
Another option is the ballistic descent.
飞船开始旋转
The spacecraft starts spinning.
并且沿着相当陡的轨道飞行 而不产生任何附加的侧移
And flies a much steeper trajectory without any additional sideways displacement.
过载在这种情况下会达到9G
The G-load in this case will increase up to 9.
当返回舱达到10.5km高时
When the capsule reaches an altitude of 10.5 km,
它的速度已经从7778m/s降到222.2m/s
its speed has already decreased from 28000 to 800 km/h.
为了进一步降低速度
In order to further decrease the speed,
降落伞盖被弹出 一组降落伞打开
the parachute cover is jettisoned and a series of parachutes are deployed.
在大气再入的最终阶段 你才真的开始听到风声
At the end of the atmospheric re-entry, you really start hearing the noise of the wind and the sound,
你终于突破了音障
you are almost breaking the sound barrier.
之后 与之前所经历的不同的是 当然 是你回到了正常的飞行的领域
Then, in the opposite direction of course you are coming back into the normal area of flying.
大约在9144m的高度 降落伞得要打开
This is around 30000 feet that the parachute has to open.
这是非常关键的时刻
This is actually a very critical moment
这是为数不多的几个在联盟号上不能手动控制的过程
and is one of the only things in the Soyuz where the crew does not have a manual override.
这只有自动系统
So this is only an automated system.
到目前为止 它都顺利运行 而且我们也有一个备用降落伞
So far, it has always worked and we also have a backup parachute
一旦主降落伞不能打开 就可以使用备用的
that can help us in case that the main will not open.
但那是极为紧急的情况下才会发生的事情
But it is also a very violent moment.
你可以想象 这个2吨重的返回舱 正在以音速穿过大气层
You can imagine this 2000 kilogram capsule that is soaring at the speed of sound through the atmosphere
然后降落伞突然从边上打开 就像小秋千一样拉着你
and then all of the sudden you have a parachute that opens on the side and that pulls on you, like a little swing.
这就像一个悠悠球一样地被拉来拉去
It is almost like a yo-yo and you see the capsule going all around.
这比在过山车上的动作还糟糕得多
It is much worse than in a roller coaster
因为运动是发生在所有方向的 对于某些宇航员来说比较恐怖
because the motion is in all directions and it is a little bit scary for some of us.
而对于其他人来讲 可能是充满乐趣的 他们可能会这么说 这种乘坐体验是最爽的
For some others it can also be fun because they are like "Wow this is the best ride I've ever had!"
几分钟后 在8.5km的高度上
Then, a few minutes later, at a height of 8.5 km,
引导伞展开了1000平方米伞盖的主降落伞
the drogue chute finally deploys the 1000 square metre canopy of the main parachute.
这将返回舱的速度降至6.1m/s
This slows the capsule down to a speed of 22 km/h.
返回舱被吊在伞下 以某一特定的角度朝向地面
The capsule is suspended under the parachute with a specific angle relative to the ground.
这个角度可以散掉返回舱再入过程中表面所积累的热量
This angle helps the capsule to dissipate the heat accumulated on its surface and structure during the re-entry.
但是在主降落伞打开后 一切都会平静下来
But then everything calms down, of course once that the main parachute has deployed.
在经历了猛烈的再入 猛烈的降落伞打开过程之后 你也平静下来
you really come to the calm air after this whole violent re-entry, the violent opening of the parachute,
之后你安全地悬挂在降落伞下 缓慢地下降到地球上
then you are hanging safely, slowly descending to the Earth underneath your parachute
事实上这是你第一次意识到
and this is actually the first time that you know:
是的 我安全了 我们会成功的！
Yes, I am safe, we are going to make it!
在5.5km上空时 朝前的隔热罩和外窗的玻璃被抛离了
At an altitude of roughly 5.5 km, the frontal heat shield and external window glass are jettisoned.
返回舱从加压储罐中释放出多余的燃料和氧气
The capsule vents excess fuel and oxygen from pressurised tanks,
以避免返回舱撞击地面时爆炸的风险
to reduce any chance of an explosion when it hits the ground.
为了对返回舱着陆适当定位
In order to position the spacecraft adequately for the landing,
主伞转换成对称状态
the main canopy switches to symmetric suspension.
这种布局可以确保宇航员的座椅放置得能够最好地吸收着陆时的冲击
This setup ensures that the cosmonauts' seats are now perfectly positioned to absorb the landing impact shock.
藏在隔热盾背后的反推火箭也准备好进行点火了
The retrorockets that were hidden behind the heat shield are prepared for firing.
在返回舱内 为了让减震器工作 宇航员的座椅会自动提升
Inside the capsule, the crew seats automatically raise in order to prepare shock absorbers.
通常 搜救人员会乘飞机或直升机
Usually, the Search and Rescue Team equipped with aircraft and helicopters
在第一个降落伞打开之前 就开始对返回舱进行跟踪
starts tracking the Soyuz capsule even before the very first parachute is deployed.
直升机会在返回舱着陆后不久着陆在附近 随后直升机上的团队会帮助返回舱乘员出舱
The helicopters land next to the capsule shortly after touch down and the team help the crew to exit.
最后 在距地面0.7m高度时
Finally, 70 cm above the ground,
6个反推火箭点火 将返回舱的速度进一步减少至1.39m/s
the six retro rockets fire to further reduce the capsule speed to approximately 5 km/h.
返回舱触地时 乘员座椅仍在向下移动
The capsule hits the ground but the crew seats continue moving down
减震器会缓冲着陆对宇航员的冲击
and shock absorbers help to make the landing softer for the crew.
软着陆实际上并不软
The soft landing is not really soft.
你要为此做好准备 用手臂抵住身体
You prepare for it by putting your arms against your body.
不要碰金属五瓶 手里握紧书本
Not touching any of the metallic parts, hold your books against you.
不可以说话
You are not talking.
舌头不要放在牙齿之间
Not to put the tongue in the middle of your teeth.
尽可能地躺坐在座位里面
and you are lying there trying to be as inside your seat as well as you can.
并等待着这样的软着陆发生
And you are waiting for this "soft landing" to happen,
which for me felt like a head-on collision between a truck and a small car
对于我来说 就像一辆卡车和小轿车的正面相撞
保罗·内斯波利于2011年5月24日的着陆
and of course I was in the small car, so when this happened it was like BA-DA-BOOM!
当然 我是在小轿车里面 这一切发生的时候就像巴拉不地一声
Everything shook, I was kind of shaking in there.
包括我在内的所有的东西都在震动
之后 一切都已过去 一切都已静止
Everything was, and then... silence everything was stopped.
那么 我看了看周围 然后看向其他乘员说着
So I looked a little bit around, and I looked at my crew members and then I said:
伙计们 欢迎回到地球
Hey guys, Welcome back to Earth!
着陆后指令长所做的第一件事情是
Once landed, one of the first actions of the crew commander is
解下连接返回舱和降落伞之间的两根绳子
to release one of the two ropes that connect the capsule to the parachute.
这是很重要的 因为在有风的情况下
This is important, as in windy conditions,
它能防止返回舱被风吹起来的降落伞拽走
it prevents the capsule from being dragged away on the ground by the inflated parachute.
你知道你在地面上了 你听到了搜救队的声音
You know that you are on the ground, you hear the voices of the rescue troops that are next to you
你知道5分钟后他们将会打开舱盖
and you know that 5 minutes later they will open up the hatch
而你可以呼吸到新鲜的空气
and you can breathe fresh air.
宇航员们现在安全返回地球了
The crew is now safely back on Earth.
不久 他们将要和家庭团聚 并开始恢复身体
They will soon be reunited with their families and begin the rehabilitation process,
在他们的非凡旅程之后
after their extraordinary journey.